In the previous lesson, we looked at this and how to create our own function that will cube a number
for us.
But in this lesson, I want to show you a bit more of an interesting example, which hopefully you can
see how functions can actually be quite useful.
In order to do this, we are going to need a list of the days of the week, because I want to play around
a bit with this list and create different functions that do different things with the list.
Okay, so let's just remember lists are special types of data types.
We looked at this in the previous lesson.
If you're not sure how to do lists, go back and visit our lesson on lists.
Here we have a list with all the days of the week.
Let me actually maybe call this something like days of Week, so it makes more sense.
Not just a list.
It's a list of days.
Okay, now we are going to create a function.
So the first function I want to define is a function that could perhaps tell us if the current day of
the week is a weekend.
So maybe you need this.
If you're working out someone's how much someone's getting paid for something.
Maybe it's different on the weekend.
Or maybe you want to write a program that tells you what days the shop is open.
Maybe their times change based on the days of the week.
So basically, I mean, you can think of different ways you could use this, but we just want to know
we want a program that can tell us straight away is it a weekend or not.
So we're going to define this function and I'm going to call it the function is weekend.
So it's almost like a question when you call it you're saying is it the weekend.
And it's going to tell us true or false.
And for this function we need to have a string parameter where the user will type in whatever day of
the week is.
So let's just call it day.
Maybe.
Okay, now the way we are going to do this is kind of like what we did in some of our other examples.
Basically, when we want to say if the day is equal to Saturday or the day is equal to Sunday, then
we want to return a value of true.
And if it is not, we want to return false.
So let's try and do that.
So if day is equal to and remember the spelling has to be exactly the same.
If I spelt this differently to how I spelt it here, then it's not going to see them as the same or
so we want to write an Or because the day does not have to be equal to Saturday and Sunday.
It's Saturday or Sunday or day is equal to equal Sunday.
Then we want to return a value of true.
In other words, yes, it is a weekend.
Else we are going to return false.
Basically it is not a weekend again.
So that's what we actually want.
True if it is false if it's not.
Now let's call this function.
So to call it we need to know its name is weekend.
And at once one parameter.
We're going to start off by just giving the function a value or a day of our choice.
So let's give it Wednesday.
I didn't print it.
So again nothing happens if you don't print your function.
Well not nothing happens.
But we don't see anything happening.
But as soon as you print it, you can see exactly what it did.
It returned this value of false because Wednesday is not a weekday.
So let's give it one that is Sunday and that's going to return true.
But remember how I said you don't want to really write programs like this that are susceptible to human
error?
Because as soon as I spell it wrong, it's telling me even I thought I wrote Sunday or no, that's not
a day of the week.
So just to make it a bit more robust.
So just to make it a bit more robust, I've created this list that we can use.
And also I'm this puts a whole lot of your other elements that you've learned in other sections into
one, hopefully reminding you of all of the things you've learned.
So let's call Days of Week and let's ask it if the full if the fourth index in the list is a weekend
day.
So remember the fourth index in the list Monday is zero, so 01234 Friday is not.
But if we then went five it gives us true.
Okay, so this is basically it's parsing days of the week five.
In other words it's parsing Saturday into this function over here.
Day then becomes Saturday and it's gone.
Is day equal to Saturday.
Yes it is return true.
So that's what this function is doing.
A cool thing about functions that return true or false values is that we can actually use them with
if statements, just like an if statement determines if something is true, then something happens.
And if it's not, something else happens, we can actually use these true and false values for that.
So I'm going to change this print statement into an if statement.
So what we want to ask.
So what we want to do is we want to say if is weekend we could say equals equals true.
But remember like we said earlier it's just saying is weekend or just saying this is the same thing
as saying if it's equal to true.
So if it's true then we would like to print something.
So let's just say yep P it's the weekend and else if it is not if it is false print still work.
Still work days.
So this is our if statement.
So now when I run it it's found days of the week index five, which was Saturday.
It's gone into this function with data Saturday and it's returned true.
So that means this whole expression becomes true.
So if it's true, print.
Yippee!
It's the weekend.
So that's what it printed.
So now let's change it to one that we know is not a weekend.
So let's just go with zero which we know should be Monday.
And if we run that oh no it's still work days.
So it did basically the opposite.
It came in.
So it was Monday.
Is it Saturday?
Sunday.
Nope.
So return false.
Then it came.
Here.
Is the weekend true?
Nope.
It's not.
We got a false from that.
So we are coming to the else here and printing this.
So yeah obviously you didn't have we didn't have to have this whole list thing here.
We could have just typed it straight in if that.
That might look a bit more simple to some of you or more easy to understand.
And again, that is going to give us this value over here.
So yeah, that's just a quick function.
How you can see that you can use true and false return values and that it becomes quite useful.
And obviously I can use this function as many times as I want.
Maybe later on I want to have another if statement that prints something else based on if it's a weekend
or not.
And you can keep on using this function as many times as you would like throughout your program.
So that's what's important with functions.
And when you're coding, one of the things you want to learn is can you create reusable blocks out of
anything?
And the quicker you can create reusable blocks, the better your coding is going to become.
Because when you know that that reusable block is working, you never have to worry about it again.
It will always work.
And so that is why functions are so powerful.
So have some fun, play with them.
You can see they really are powerful.
All your knowledge, all your wisdom is now coming together and functions is the next exciting step.